<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd on May the 29th. 1673. in one of His Majesties licens'd meetings in Devon</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B10006</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">69648924</idno>
  <idno type="VID">185077</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240867868</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183740</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">69648924</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B10006)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2886:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd on May the 29th. 1673. in one of His Majesties licens'd meetings in Devon</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. P. and are to be sold by Michael Hide, Bookseller in Exon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O. T. --  Isaiah XL, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:185077:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>IN ONE OF His Majesties <hi>LICENS'D MEETINGS</hi> in <hi>DEVON.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of bird and dragon on either side of a chalice</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. P.</hi> and are to be sold by <hi>Michael Hide,</hi> Bookseller in <hi>Exon,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:185077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185077:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>YOƲ have this Sermon <hi>verbatim,</hi> as it was preach'd, and taken in <hi>Short-hand.</hi> The Author himself knows nothing of its Publication; <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> far was he from designing, or preparing it for <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at end. However he needs not be asham'd to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e it abroad, 'twill recommend it self to all serious <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d ingenuous persons.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:185077:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:185077:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Isa. 40. 3.</bibl>
               <q>The voice of him that cryeth in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord, make strait in the desart an High-way for our God.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> in his 2 <hi>Epist. 1 ch. 19 v.</hi> recommends unto the Faithful, to whom he wrote, the <hi>word of Prophesie,</hi> as he termeth it, and commends them for <hi>heeding</hi> of it; They <hi>did well,</hi> he saith, in so doing. That <hi>word</hi> which <hi>Peter</hi> means, is indeed <hi>a light shining in this dark place of the Earth,</hi> where we walk not by sight; 'Tis the <hi>great Foundation</hi> of Faith, and Hope, until the day of Glory dawn, and we in Gods own Light, see all Light. But that worthy Recommendation the Apostle seconds in the two following Verses, with a weighty Reason; <hi>Knowing</hi> (saith he) <hi>that no Prophesie of the Scripture is of any private Interpretation:</hi> That is, Not of any private humane Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:185077:4"/> or Extraction; 'Tis not an effect of any mans <hi>peculiar</hi> temper, or more than <hi>ordinary</hi> skill, That this is meant, the after-words in the same Context do plainly evince; for, saith <hi>Peter, The Prophesie in old time, came not by the will of man; but holy men of God spake as they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the holy Ghost.</hi> The Spirit of God, (the publick Interpreter, and Revealer of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and Mind of God), He inspired the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and was the Author of their word: The things (my Beloved) which are <hi>reported</hi> and <hi>affirmed</hi> in Scripture are (many of them) evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Divine, The Heart of Man could not have <hi>conceived</hi> them: The Commands and Precepts in Scripture, are (many of them at least) evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently Divine. The Spirit of a Man could not have formed them, nor enjoined them, as there they are. The Promises and Threatnings in Scripture have Characters of a Divine Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal upon them in like manner, they could not be of Man; And I confess, I much incline to think, that the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> comprehends even all these under the Prophesie of the Scriptures,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:185077:4"/> which he speaketh of. But Prophesie, in the strict sense of it, and Foretelling of things to come, This must needs have a <hi>peculiar</hi> Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this behalf. That of this nature, which is in Scripture, is, in the very eye of Reason, more illustriously Supernatural, and Divine. But I tarry too long in Generals.</p>
            <p>The particular Text which I have been cast upon for the present Time and Occasion, for our holy <hi>exercise</hi> now, (my much Respected and Beloved) is of this Quality; A <hi>little,</hi> but a <hi>remarkable</hi> piece of a <hi>remarkable Prophesie;</hi> It is a few of the words which this Man of God <hi>Isaiah,</hi> spake as he was moved by the Holy Ghost: And I cannot but conclude, from what hath been already intimated, That <hi>we shall do well to give heed unto them.</hi> Yea, if the same <hi>Spirit</hi> by which <hi>Isaiah</hi> spake them, vouchsafe to assist us, in our poor degree, we shall profit by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The voice of him that cryeth in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. These are the words.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:185077:5"/>
            <p>Now at my entrance upon them, I doubt, I shall a little surprise you: For from a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prediction, (as the words are) I shall raise a general Doctrinal Observation; and the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation I shall lay down, before I at all open the Prediction: The Observation too at first sight, will seem to have no alliance with the Prediction: But I hope, upon a little progress ye will neither <hi>wonder</hi> at my <hi>method,</hi> nor <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve</hi> the <hi>matter.</hi> To me they have seemed <hi>both</hi> convenient. The Observation then, or Doctrine which I spake of, and shall begin with, is this:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Doct. That</hi> God in the course of his Providence over the present World, doth make, sometimes, Magnificent and Royal Manifestation of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</q>
            <p>This I take to be a <hi>genuine issue</hi> of the words, and I make it a <hi>foundation</hi> for the <hi>Exposition</hi> of them, and the <hi>general Subject</hi> of my Discourse. The same God who is <hi>named</hi> and <hi>concerned</hi> in it, be present with us, and grant us some <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease</hi> in the <hi>understanding</hi> of his <hi>word,</hi> and in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:185077:5"/> the <hi>good knowledg</hi> of <hi>Himself;</hi> even for <hi>his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> sake, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
            <p>But to the matter: I shall first clear the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression</hi> of the Text, and of the Observation; and next, enquire into the <hi>thing intended</hi> by the Prophet; and lastly, accommodate, as I may, the <hi>whole</hi> unto the present <hi>occasion,</hi> and our <hi>use.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. For the <hi>expression:</hi> Great Princes do put forth their Princely Power and Wisdom, in the ordinary, constant <hi>government</hi> of their People, and <hi>ordering</hi> their great Affairs; and they are hereupon <hi>acknowledged,</hi> and <hi>awfully honoured</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all their Dominions: But sometimes <hi>they</hi> come abroad, and appear in <hi>special</hi> Pomp, and Princely Glory; As when they Ride in State on special occasions in Peace; or when they March in the Front of Puissant Armies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to War: Then the whole Country seeth them, and makes Shouts and Acclamations to them. (Beloved) God is the Great King, the Soveraign of the Universe, his Divine Power, and Wisdom, and Righteousness,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:185077:6"/> and Mercy do <hi>operate</hi> and <hi>appear</hi> in the <hi>ordinary</hi> course of Nature, and in his <hi>common</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and disposing of all things: Oh that he might be <hi>acknowledged</hi> and <hi>honoured</hi> hereupon in all places of his Dominion. But sometimes he <hi>ariseth,</hi> as the expression is, <hi>Psal.</hi> 12. 5. some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he <hi>comes abroad,</hi> as may be said, and as indeed the term in effect is, <hi>Psal.</hi> 96. 13. and divers other places. That is, he worketh some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in an <hi>unusual</hi> manner, in a manner <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought</hi> of, and above all <hi>appearing Probabilities;</hi> sometimes, he sheweth his Royal Greatness with Pomp, as I may speak, that every one <hi>seeth</hi> and <hi>admireth,</hi> and saith, <hi>'tis He;</hi> sometimes he doth <hi>marvellous Acts, great things,</hi> as the Scripture stileth them: Now, this I call his Magnificent and Royal Manifestation of Himself. And 'tis <hi>such</hi> an effect that my Text refers unto, as doth evidently appear by what followeth in this same Prediction here, at the <hi>5th. ver. The glory of the Lord,</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see it together.</hi> The <hi>plenary</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> Manifestation of the Glory of God is to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:185077:6"/> be in Heaven alone, there within the Vail, there only is the Beatifick Vision of him; But even here on Earth without the Vail, some seasons be, when he gives <hi>signal</hi> tokens of his Glory unto the <hi>conviction</hi> of men, and unto the high <hi>affecting</hi> of their hearts. Such an <hi>event,</hi> I say, the Prophet here in this Prophesie foretells. But to come nearer the words, I must advance a step farther in that <hi>resemblance</hi> of which I have made use: As Princes then when they go forth in State have the way prepared for them, and as much as may be made plain and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; there is a diligent cleansing, and righting of every Street and every Road through which they are to pass, and oftentimes Order is publickly given, Proclamation made unto that end, as ye know; so here, <hi>The voice of him that cryeth in the wilderness, Prepare ye the way of the Lord,</hi> saith the Prophet. The purpose of God was represented to the Prophet under the <hi>likeness</hi> of a <hi>Royal Progress</hi> intended; and thus he in his rich and copious manner doth express it; he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates a <hi>Proclamation</hi> (as may be said) to <hi>clear</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:185077:7"/> and <hi>level</hi> the way before the coming of the Lord: This is the voice of the <hi>Cryer</hi> here. Not that there should be literally such a thing in all that the Prophesie intendeth; But the meaning is, that God intended to manifest himself in a <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and <hi>Splendid</hi> manner; would work in a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable,</hi> and an <hi>unusual,</hi> and <hi>magnificent</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; 'tis said, <hi>Make strait in the desert an High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for our God;</hi> In the Desert, where there was no way, nothing but <hi>Hill</hi> and <hi>Dale,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>winding,</hi> and <hi>uneven,</hi> and <hi>unpassable</hi> ground. He signifies, the Lord would do what there was no <hi>visible</hi> means to do; would do what no one did imagine how it could be done. And this I take to be the true reason of the Prophets expression; <hi>Ye that attend unto it, judg of it.</hi> God would reveal his Glory, as in a Royal manner; in token of this, <hi>The voice</hi> (saith the Prophet) <hi>of him that cryeth, Prepare the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having taken this view of the <hi>expression,</hi> we must next enquire into the thing <hi>intended</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; Now ye may please to follow me, and observe to this end:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:185077:7"/>1. That God doth sometimes <hi>manifest Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> as ye have heard, unto <hi>Judgment; strangely,</hi> and <hi>wonderfully</hi> punishing the <hi>Scandals,</hi> and <hi>Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,</hi> and <hi>Refractoriness</hi> of People. Of this you read in the <hi>26th.</hi> Chapter of this <hi>Prophesie</hi> of <hi>Isaiah, 21 v. The Lord cometh out of his place,</hi> (saith the Prophet there) (as the Soveraign and Judg of all the Earth) <hi>to punish the Inhabitants of the Earth for their Iniquity.</hi> Thus the Lord came forth when he brought the Flood upon the old World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. Thus when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that Luxurious Plain, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. Thus he came forth when he smote <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> and gave them up into the Hands of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar, 2 Chron.</hi> 36. 17. And thus again, when he overthrew, after some Threescore and ten years, the whole Empire of that same <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> and laid that great, proud <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> he had built utterly waste, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 25. And thus God will come, in due time, to Judg the <hi>Grand Harlot</hi> of the Earth, the <hi>mystical Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Rev.</hi> 17. 8. Gods <hi>full revelation</hi> of his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:185077:8"/> will be at the last, great Day: But mean time he will preserve in the World some sense that he is Just, and doth Judg. Besides, at that great day, 'tis but particular Persons that shall be Judged; There will be no States, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms then; therefore the Lord visits those in the present World, where only they have their Existence: And when the <hi>measure</hi> of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of Kingdoms is full, then he saith unto them, as he did to <hi>Israel, Amos 4. 12. Prepare to meet your God, ye sinful People.</hi> He judgeth them with Terror, and there is no Counsel, nor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence against him. Let not the most Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, or Triumphant Nations be secure. But our present occasion (Beloved), and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise to which my Text doth refer, is of no such dismal Nature. Therefore note,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes God <hi>comes forth,</hi> and <hi>manifests Himself</hi> in Magnifick Royal manner, to <hi>shew mercy,</hi> to <hi>refresh,</hi> to <hi>deliver,</hi> to <hi>restore,</hi> to <hi>build up,</hi> to <hi>bless,</hi> and <hi>put into a State of Renown upon Earth.</hi> He is <hi>good</hi> with the very <hi>goodness</hi> of an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty and ever Blessed God; and sometimes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:185077:8"/> he makes <hi>glorious,</hi> and almost <hi>incredible</hi> Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations of it; Unto him be Glory. Thus he did when he first brought <hi>Israel</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and led them into their Inheritance, <hi>Then his way was prepared in the wilderness indeed:</hi> But with what <hi>glororious Pomp</hi> did he make his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress:</hi> The <hi>strength</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that ancient migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Kingdom was utterly broken, and fainted; the Waters of the <hi>Red Sea</hi> were divided, and cast up in Heaps on one Hand, and on the other; the Mountains did burn and shake; the Clouds and Sky thundered; Nations upon every side did tremble; All Nature did Resent the Presence of the God of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob;</hi> so wonderfully did he work for that People then. Here was a right <hi>Stately, Royal shewing forth</hi> of his <hi>Magnificence</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty.</hi> Other passages of a like kind, I might recount. But,</p>
            <p>There are, particularly, two concerned in my Text, and them I must particularly insist upon a little: The first of them, (Good Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren),
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:185077:9"/> was, The Lords bringing back that same People of <hi>Israel</hi> from their Captivity in <hi>Babylon:</hi> This was such a <hi>manifestation</hi> of him, as I have spoken of. Now that we may take a little account hereof, pray consider the Calamity of that People; when they had been, as it were, long sick, and weakned, by divers sad events; they were in the close (as I may say) <hi>utterly slain: Multitudes</hi> fell by the <hi>Sword; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes</hi> dyed with <hi>Famine; multitudes</hi> with <hi>Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> and the sorrowful <hi>remainder</hi> were carried away <hi>Slaves</hi> into a strange Land; their own in the mean time was devoured, and laid quite waste; their Cities were burnt with Fire; and (oh the grief of all) <hi>Jerusalem</hi> it self, and the <hi>Temple</hi> in it, (both rich Cabinet, and rare Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el) were consumed together. Then the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Publick Service of God did utterly cease, and there was left no solemn Assembly in all the World to worship him. This was doleful, and verily deserving a whole Book of Lamentations. But think farther of their <hi>hopelesness</hi> in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy case; The Dry Bones in the Vision of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:185077:9"/>
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37th. <hi>chap.</hi> were an apt <hi>Emblem</hi> of their <hi>Condition.</hi> There was no likelihood at all of their <hi>Reviving;</hi> There appeared no <hi>way,</hi> no <hi>means</hi> in the Earth for their <hi>deliverance.</hi> Well might <hi>Jeremiah</hi> express it as he did, and say, <hi>Lam. 1. 2. The daughter of Zion weepeth sore in the night, and the Tears are on her Cheeks, and among all her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers there was none to comfort her.</hi> None at all, this was <hi>dark night</hi> indeed, horrour of darkness, and to say true, <hi>a shadow of death.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the <hi>provocations</hi> that had been on their parts, and notwithstanding all this <hi>wrath</hi> on Gods part, yet he did determine to be Himself a <hi>Light</hi> unto them. He had taken order indeed aforehand by our Prophet that they should be comforted, effectually comforted, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ye, comfort ye my People, saith your God, speak ye comfortably to Jerusalem.</hi> I, but how so? <hi>Cry unto her that her warfare is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned,</hi> Isa. 40. 1, 2. It was foretold there should be an end, and issue out of even this their great, and desperate calamity. Oh but could that be, was there any possibility of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:185077:10"/> it! Yes. The Lord undertook to do it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, to come in royal manner and do it; And as he <hi>undertook</hi> so he <hi>performed.</hi> He came in due time, and at his coming obstacles were <hi>removed,</hi> bonds <hi>loosed,</hi> dry bones <hi>gathered flesh,</hi> and <hi>lived, Judah</hi> was <hi>delivered.</hi> He blasted the Glory of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> that had brought this calamity upon them, and that became as the flower of the field, <hi>vers. the 8th.</hi> And he inclined the spirit of that generous victorious <hi>Persian</hi> to set them at liberty. And so those <hi>Jews</hi> as from their Graves returned to their dear Country. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> and the <hi>Temple</hi> rose up out of their Ashes, were again builded, God was worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped again, their dark night became light. At this the <hi>Jews</hi> themselves were ravisht; They sung, <hi>When the Lord turned the Captivity of Zion then we were like them that dream.</hi> And the Heathen on each side of them were astonisht, and convinc'd at it, and acknowledged the God of Israel. Then said they among the Heathen, <hi>The Lord hath done great things for them,</hi> Psal. 126. 1, 2.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:185077:10"/>
            <p>Lo, here was, (my Beloved) here was a <hi>Magnificent</hi> and <hi>real Manifestation</hi> of God, a <hi>making bare of his Arm, so as all flesh saw it.</hi> Here was a King-like coming forth of God to shew his People mercy; And well might the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet say, <hi>The voice of one crying in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, Prepare the way.</hi> This is one particular which is directly and primarily intended, in the Text, and in this Prophesie; And who should despair of the Church of God, even at the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est ebb. But this was that I say which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet did primarily, and (as I may term it) lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally here foretell; but God had yet a greater Mystery in it, and guided the words of the Prophet so as to signifie the same withal. The truth is, (Brethren) Gods great purpose was to send his own Son into the world, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his works, and (generally) all his words from the beginning had a <hi>Tincture</hi> of, and <hi>Reference</hi> to this. Many times when other things were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permost, and most in view, yet they were but as the <hi>Shell,</hi> this was as the <hi>Kernel</hi> inclosed in them. The greatest <hi>Reference</hi> lay to our blessed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:185077:11"/> Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. Now thus it was in this <hi>Prediction</hi> which I am handling, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from the Captivity of Babylon,</hi> lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permost, and was first in sight, but under it was signified, <hi>The coming of the Messiah,</hi> and of the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven by him.</hi> This is the second, the other great particular, of which I gave you intimation. Our Lord and Saviour the Son of God, ('tis true) came in great meanness, and the very form of a Servant, so he lived, and so he died. Let no person ever grudg to be put into a mean estate. He came in great abasement, but never was the like <hi>Manifestation</hi> of God from the beginning, nor shall be to the end. That very meanness there was, made it more mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous and magnificent. God was, God was in that <hi>despised</hi> in that <hi>Crucified Jesus,</hi> as never in any other. God was in him <hi>Reconciling</hi> the world unto himself; <hi>Breaking</hi> the Head of the old Serpent, and <hi>destroying</hi> his work, <hi>laying</hi> the Foundations of new Heavens, and a new Earth. God was in him <hi>executing,</hi> and <hi>acting,</hi> those great things upon which the hope of all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:185077:11"/> former ages had been builded, and the faith of all after-generations was to be fixed; things that neither eye had seen, nor ear heard, nor heart of Man could ever have conceived, if God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had not revealed them. Nay, the same Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus was <hi>very God, manifested in the flesh;</hi> Oh magnificent, beyond compare, and divinely roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al coming forth of the most High into the World! who is able to set forth, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all the glory of it. Men and Angels shall to eternity admire, and praise him for it.</p>
            <p>But (Beloved) in this my Text for its part was very punctually fulfilled, and more expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than it had been at the deliverance from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> Before this coming of God in Jesus Christ, <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi> really was, <hi>the voice of one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderness, Prepare the way of the Lord make his paths straight.</hi> This the same <hi>John</hi> affirmed of himself, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 23. And this the other Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelists with one consent affirm likewise of him, <hi>Mat. 3. 3. Mar. 1. 3. Luk</hi> 3. 4. The coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, therefore, was a thing eminently <hi>intended</hi> in this Prophesie. And then,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:185077:12"/> if ever the glory of the Lord was revealed, and all flesh did, or well might see his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now thus you may see the Text compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently opened, and the observation which I have raised, also cleared, and verified, <hi>God in the course of his Providence over the present world, doth sometimes make magnifick and royal Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations of himself;</hi> he hath so done indeed.</p>
            <p>Now my dear Country-men and Friends, a passage, I will not say <hi>equal,</hi> but in a <hi>degree</hi> of this nature, a passage of this nature in our own Land, the <hi>present day</hi> of the <hi>Year</hi> doth bring to our <hi>Remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To exaggerate and to exalt the Acts and Successes of Kings and Rulers, above their <hi>just measure</hi> is an immodest and ignoble flattery; On the other hand to depretiate and to debase them below their <hi>real value</hi> is gross injury and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The respects of Decency and Equity, of Conscience, and Religion, engage us to weigh the truth in all things, and judg according there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; this I have aimed to do. And hereupon,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:185077:12"/> I must needs say, <hi>That the restoring of Royal Government in our Land,</hi> and <hi>the restoring of it in the Royal Person of our Soveraign,</hi> this was a <hi>Magnifick and royal effect of the hand of God,</hi> by whom Kings raign. Ye that are of Age may remember what our condition was. If some things did please <hi>a part</hi> of these Nations, yet the <hi>whole body</hi> reeled to and fro as having no firm ground to stand upon; We were as if these brave Islands had been taken off from their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient bottom, and floated, and been driven here and there on the Seas that do surround them. The most partial (I perswade my self) cannot, will not, gainsay it. The <hi>Setling</hi> of Authority and Rule upon a <hi>steady Basis,</hi> is the <hi>real strength</hi> and <hi>confirmation</hi> of States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, 'tis of bottom consequence unto all their welfare. And when for want of this Mens Hearts did well nigh fail at home, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did deride, and contemn, and design upon us from abroad, it pleased God himself to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpose, and <hi>to prepare a way in the Desart,</hi> a way where none was. It pleased God to come
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:185077:13"/> himself, and to re-erect the Throne, and to place our dear Country upon its proper Basis, to fix our Government; as if hereto had been <hi>the voice of him that crieth.</hi> The way was in an unusual, in an unthought of manner prepared prepared suddenly, Hearts <hi>inclined,</hi> Obstacles <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and the thing <hi>effected.</hi> I know (Beloved) ye are ready to join with me in a just Acclamation to it, and to say, It was the Lords doing, and is memorable in our account. 'Tis plain, God would not have it done by Plots or Insurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or force of Arms, he would not have the Kings way smoothed with the Peoples blood. No, the God of Peace determined to bring, and brought home the King in Peace: He is that <hi>God that ruleth in all the Kingdoms of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> World, and doth even whatsoever pleaseth him.</hi> Let us humbly and earnestly beseech him to <hi>Preserve</hi> the KING, to <hi>stablish</hi> the Throne, to be <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> to our dear Country; to <hi>second</hi> his former wonderful works, with <hi>renewed effects</hi> of his Divine Presence in all our need. Let us beseech him, that he please to make both <hi>Head</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:185077:13"/>
               <hi>Body,</hi> both <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> faithfully mindful of, grateful for, answerable to his great Obligations upon them; they are great indeed, and what should <hi>England</hi> render, All, both its Princes, and People for his Benefits towards them. But (my Beloved) for our selves, ye know Religion, as to the <hi>main</hi> of it, is, respect for, and nearnest to God most high. He sheweth himself in his ordinary works, and his tokens are new every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But sometimes he reveals his Glory, convinceth very Heathens themselves. He plainly manifested his Glory in Christ Jesus with unspeakable Grace; Oh <hi>know</hi> we him, and encrease in that <hi>knowledg</hi> of him; <hi>Believe</hi> him, and <hi>encrease</hi> in that <hi>believing</hi> him; <hi>Fear</hi> him, and <hi>encrease</hi> in that <hi>fear</hi> of him; Be near him in heart and life, and encrease in that divine nearness to him; Let our Religious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness be in <hi>reality,</hi> for that God, the great object of it really is, is <hi>really</hi> glorious, <hi>really</hi> governeth now, and will judg with supream Authority hereafter. Be <hi>indeed</hi> a godly Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:185077:14"/> since he <hi>indeed</hi> is God, and filleth every Age and Country with such Tokens of his Glory. Withal, trust we in him, He hath often done great things, things unlookt for, unthought of; He hath appeared to <hi>help</hi> the <hi>needy</hi> when there was no other help at all <hi>appearing.</hi> In the Churches, or in your own lowest Condition be not dismayed, nor let your hearts fail within you.</p>
            <p>To close all for this time. Let me be in my poor measure <hi>the voice of one that crieth,</hi> and (much respected and beloved in Christ) <hi>Prepare ye the way of the Lord;</hi> For your parts, (not to speak of other things) God cometh to you in the Gospel, mighty to save; Oh let his way be ready that your Souls may live and rejoyce in his Salvation; Jesus Christ cometh in the Sacrament, ye that are particularly concerned, <hi>Prepare his way,</hi> examine, humble ye, reform ye, covet fresh evidences, and ensuring of your Union with him, that ye may draw nigh, and make his faithful pledges unto you, and feed your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:185077:14"/> Soul unto eternal life. All of us, one with another in the name of God, and his Christ prepare we for his <hi>last,</hi> and <hi>greatest,</hi> his most <hi>Magnifick</hi> and <hi>Royal Manifestation of himself.</hi> Prepare we for that dreadful day when Christ shall appear in the Clouds, and all Nations be gathered before him, and every Soul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to what hath been done in the Body, make ready in simplicity, and with earnest endeavour now, strive to be, and to do in all things, that ye may be then found in peace, without spot, and blameless, and be taken into his own, eternal, blessed King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which can never be troubled, never be shaken.</p>
            <p>Now, the Lord himself <hi>teach</hi> you all, and <hi>direct</hi> your Hearts, and <hi>Prepare your way,</hi> and be in the midst of you to all gracious saving Purposes for his Names sake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>